uh we gotta go fast or we won't die
right uh by the way I want to play you a
song uh before I
go and actually is for my
wife uh and I forgot all the words
okay so I'll sing it the same that I
sing the Chinese
song
okay so we have
to yeah Vos okay here we
go number
five Brian the
prayer living fire living number
[Music]
five and here's the picture number
4426 yeah if you ever took a DCI course
uh you know what this picture
is we call it coffee
meditation and this is uh the best way
to make your seeds
strong our habit when we go to
sleep we start to
worry about our
life I don't have enough money
my wife or my husband's
unhappy I don't know what my kids maybe
they're going to grow up to be gangster
I don't
know and uh in the nighttime before we
sleep is a very the uh Prana is very uh
exposed and it's very easy to be
influenced by negative f
and then it disturbs your
sleep so the advice of the you heard me
say it in DCI for 12 or 13 years 15
years always sleep in a good
mood and the most important practice is
coffee
meditation it has nothing to do with
coffee I don't know why they call coffee
man actually if you drink coffee before
you sleep you won't have a
good so uh when you put your head on the
pillow think about the best thing you
did today for other
people okay that's all and your mind
will fight with you
your mind is like a bad dog on a
leash like Rosa has this dog Lucas
okay he just does what he
wants he goes and jumps on
people she's
like your mind is like that when you're
asleep and your mind wants to think
about oh I have so many problems you
then you got to put this rope on him
shut up come
back we're going to think about
something good we did for somebody else
today and many many uh teachings in DCI
for
example they come from the ancient
books and if you want to know where the
meditation
coffee meditation came from it's this
page which is very
cool okay uh which is the fifth of the
five
powers is
prayer and it says here and I'll read it
in Tibet okay uh we're on number five
you
guys yeah nice
[Music]
uh whatever good thing you did today for
somebody
else when you are have your head on the
pillow and when you are falling
asleep uh think about it bring it to
mind and and dedicate it to your bodh
SAA life okay
that's all that's the source for coffee
meditation
uh did we finish off
five number
three I don't what is number
three I guess he's going to cover it
later I hope let's see
okay he doesn't cover it oh wait he got
it
okay I I'll cover it let's cover the
five death ones and I maybe it comes up
okay okay I'm on D need you
guys those are the five powers for when
you're
alive let's cover the five powers for as
you
die and this is called
po so it's very very famous in other
Tibetan
traditions there's a practice called
POA and this is like you were a bad
person your whole
life and then as you're
dying you send your mind to
Heaven if it was that easy no one would
not go to
heaven so in in our tradition
if if you spent your whole life not
thinking about other
people there's no magic you can do
suddenly you're going to go to heaven it
doesn't work like
that if it work like that then Buddha
will just teach everybody Po and we
don't need all
these 300,000
books
so he says uh I will teach you real
Po and that's the PO of a bodh
sappa okay so here and it's the five
powers and the root text says uh use
those five powers as you
die
uh andet so there's the tradition in
other
lineages when you're dying you
go or you
go and then you go to heaven you
know if it's that easy everybody can
just HIIT and fo and you
know it doesn't it doesn't work like
that you can't live your whole life
being selfish and then you hick and F
and then you're okay you know it doesn't
work like
that uh now he's going to do the five
according to how to
die uh now he has number three okay I
don't know why he decided to do number
three
here yeah may I die with the motivation
to help other people
[Music]
l
l what's
that it's
Hebrew why did you forsake me you know
why why did you leave why did you leave
me who said
that Jesus on the cross like what's
going on you
know I thought you were going to take
care of
me why you why you leaving me you know
and then suddenly the whole thing
changes and on the cross uh he gives his
life for other
people I I kind of like to think that
Jesus was using the five powers of
death first he says L which means why
why why did you forsake
me and it's not in all the gospels only
one
gospel uh and then then he says I I give
my life for others you
know so I think for us it's going to be
similar the car is going to hit
you what's going
on and then uh suddenly you will
remember BH sa you
know oh I have to die like a bodh
sappa and I dedicate the pain of my
death that other people will not have
pain in their
death
then that's what makes Jesus Jesus
right that cross a
crucifixion
uh it's a murder instrument it's a it's
like a
gun it's a way to kill
somebody and but it changed
meaning Jesus gave his life for other
people
and as he's dying he say I will I will
take everybody else's
problems oh oh Lamb of God oh Lamb of
God it means uh in the in the ancient
times in the Jewish
tradition uh once a
year in
Jerusalem they will have a special
ceremony
and everybody will put their bad seeds
in the in one
lamb and then they will take it outside
of the city and they will kill
it and they think this way we are
killing our bad seeds or something like
that then Jesus is like don't kill all
those nice little
lambs I will be your
name I I will take all those bad
seeds and you can kill
me and I will take them so that's the
number
three okay I will take your bad
seeds and I will die with
them so can we guess what's the living
number three from this
one
yeah I I'm always when I'm alive or
whether I'm dying I'm always taking
other people's
problems I will eat your
problems I will take your problems and I
I everybody looks very serious
especially
Aisha but actually we should be happy
right I don't know it's like uh
I don't know if you can take everybody's
problems and then and then jump off a
cliff or something I'm I'm not saying
I'm not saying to do
that but uh the idea is
that so you don't have to wait until you
die you can take other people's troubles
all the
time but especially when you
die you can imagine you are taking all
of
them to the other
world all right so we finished number
three when you do it when you're alive
it's the living one when you do it when
you're dead is the Dead one it's taking
other people's
troubles uh the Pure White seed for when
you die
right what was it for when you're
alive what was
it
prioritize share the good
seed
okay oh I'm sorry yeah yeah yeah find
the
best there's lots of good things you can
do find the best
okay when you die it's a little bit
different and it's that uh so my parents
got cancer almost the same
time and uh my mother got a very bad
breast
cancer and my father got a very bad uh
lung
cancer
and my father was a big strong
guy and he said I'm GNA fight this
cancer you
know I will beat this
cancer and then he had a long painful
death you
know
unhappy and it was difficult for
everybody and I I was with him almost
all day every
day then uh when he
died to figure out his
finances it took one
year and he was a big big
businessman after one year fighting with
the lawyers you know many many many uh
meetings this
uh the lawyer uh came to
me and he had a
watch and he said
here that's
it that's what you
get you know your father's life was a
mess and his finances were a
mess and you get one you get one
watch from many million dollar projects
you
know and it was very painful for the
whole family to cuz my his wife didn't
know where to live or things like that
you
know then my
mom we were poor our whole
life her grandmother was very her mother
was very
wealthy she helped to her family helped
to start Chevrolet company
GMC extremely
wealthy then she told my mom if you
marry that guy I won't give
you1 and she kept the
promise and she didn't have we my mom
was a school
teacher and we we even didn't have
enough food sometimes you
know
then uh suddenly her mother
died and my mom got
cancer then her mother
died then suddenly my mom is
wealthy but she has
cancer and she she said as we are four
brothers and she said sit down in the
kitchen
then she I want to show you something
she's like this you
know and and we're
like and she says see there's a bump you
know I'm gonna I think I'm GNA
die let's let's
prepare let's get everything
ready and for like six
months it was a very fun family
project I'm going to die about this
time and you're going to take care of
this you're going to take care of this
[Music]
and and I'm gonna you're going to have
money in this Bank your money is in this
Bank you
know and she timed it perfect you
know on the day she died her bank
account hit
zero
and everything uh shared with everybody
and many Charities very kindly very very
beautifully
okay that's the white
seed practice the white seed power for
when you
die take all of your
resources and make a plan okay and don't
be
surprised like start
now start this
week I I did mine not perfect but I did
it pretty
well like every translation I ever did
it's about 50,000
Pages they went to the lawyer they are
public domain nobody can sell them uh
they are
they are public now
legally so you have to take care of it
before you before you die
okay Martin Luther King Martin Luther
King he said I have a
dream it's his most famous
[Music]
speech he didn't in his he didn't write
a clear will and he was killed
suddenly and then he died
suddenly and
uh so we don't know who owns those
words it's illegal to use those words uh
in public I have a
dream you have to pay $5 million to his
cousin you
know so that's bad
planning okay and the white seed for
dying
well is a get ready okay all your
stuff take care of your
kids have somebody ready for your
kids you know just get it ready
now and then if you don't if you don't
need it for 25 30 50 years that's
good I get I I got it ready and I gave
it to my lawyer and Veronica knows him
and she knows his phone number and
everything's
ready and she's like don't talk about it
it's bad luck you
know
I said no it's bad luck to not talk
about
it you know we have to be
ready so that's the white
seed all
right next one um uh okay we have time I
will tell you some depressing
stories about people who were attached
to their stuff they're so attached to
couldn't make a plan what to do with it
after they
die then he says uh there was a monk uh
so monk is supposed to have only two or
three
possessions or F five right sh we
allowed to have our
clothes we allowed to have an
um we allowed to have a eating
Bowl we allowed to have a
SI for sving the
water
why we allowed to have
it we are supposed to SI the water from
the river before we drink it so we don't
kill small
animals so and so why are we only
supposed to have like four or five
things so when we're meditating we're
not thinking about those extra shoes we
have then uh you know you can
focus then this monk but it's a funny
thing even the monk only has three three
four things they get very attached to
them so uh there was a monk who was
attached to his
Bull and uh he was reborn as a
snake and he threatened the
Buddha and then uh in a
forest in the BOS we are in the BOS room
now uh
and and then you know he burned up the
snake burned up the forest burned
up uh there was another M there was
another person who buried some
gold they do this in the where in the
country where you don't have a bank that
you can
trust
why Indian women wear so much gold pure
gold 24 karat
gold that's their bank
account because they cannot lock their
their door because their house is made
of palm Palm
leaves and the banks are all
crooked the most unsafe place to put
your money is a
bank so uh they buy pure gold and then
when they work in the fields they are
wearing their bank
account so uh another story of someone
who turned all their assets into
gold
and uh they were born as a snake
again and eventually Buddha forced the
snake to show him the gold and the Bad
Karma was clean something
like here's the most depressing
one number 30
4430 yeah uh these are are maggots okay
supposed to
be these are the worms that become a
fly their favorite food is human
meat I found a picture of magots eating
somebody's eye and then I decided not to
use
it uh but this is a story about somebody
who was very attached to their
body and they're always looking in the
mirror and you
know you know and
uh they
died and then uh guess what they were
born they were born as a maggot inside
their own inside their
body it's like on on Monday she is's
trying to do the uh eye makeup you
know and then on Friday she is eating
that
[Music]
eye okay got
it all right we we don't have to work on
that
one okay yeah he says uh if you're gonna
get ready to die
uh try to get some distance from your
body you know this body is uh
hopeless uh take good care of it but
don't get a touch to
it okay it's our responsibility to feed
it
Well yoga size it
well
keep it
healthy but don't get attached to
it okay and that's actually
dangerous okay all
[Music]
right okay
um yeah there's a story about a monk who
was attached to some
silver and and then
uh I don't know he was born as a frog
and he had a little piece of silver in
his little hands like
[Music]
that uh then he has a small uh he has a
small paragraph about people who have
trouble dying they have trouble letting
go
and he says we have to be ready to
go and it's unhealthy to struggle at the
end so it's okay to fight your death
that's
okay you know everybody says they're not
going to do chemotherapy and then they
all do
chemotherapy okay that's okay you know
uh even five extra minutes is important
for
us if we can do a chemotherapy and we
can stay alive for extra week or or one
month it's very it's very
good maybe during that time we we we can
do some good
practice so to fight to stay stay alive
is is a good
thing
but uh when when the time is
there then don't
fight Let It Go and and be peace be at
peace and think of all the good things
you've been
doing don't be scared okay let it go and
look ahead
and uh think about your good
seeds we are all not perfect
people we all make lots of mistakes
every
day I made lots of mistakes
yesterday but uh when you
die then let it go and think about the
good things you
did and die die in
peace okay don't don't worry about
it all
right then there's a funny story
here about the guy uh who couldn't let
go he's a monk and he he couldn't let go
and he's he he couldn't
die there's people like that you know
very stubborn people
they will stay alive extra two weeks or
something then there was one monkey was
having this problem he's
[Music]
like then the Llama said you don't want
to go to
heaven I don't know about heaven is true
or not I don't
know then the llama's like
listen I I got some
information in the heaven the churos are
amazing then the guy's
like then he died
happy then he Let It Go by the way it's
not Cho in the text it's a butter salt
tea
okay
same same thing
right for me it's going to be
churo uh then he has some instructions
what number is he on yeah he's on number
four now he's going to go to number
four what is number
four
no destruction Destroyer yeah
Destroyer so here's the death version of
number four
uh destroy your bad seeds as you
die like do some
important uh four powers as before you
die take the most important bad things
you
did and uh confess them do your four
powers uh try to remember the worst
things they
do and uh destroy means destroy them
with the four
powers okay and then he says if you have
taken Diamond weight
teachings uh try to do your
sad especially where you become the
Buddha uh and if it's possible uh have a
llama give you another
empowerment uh while you're
dying
[Music]
okay yeah and then he says uh you might
want to not wait until you're dying to
do the for
Powers because sometimes we die
unexpected
right like so many people I know like
suddenly car hit them I there's a lady
at the three jewels in New
York very
beautiful young healthy yoga
teacher rides her bike
everywhere got hit by a truck on the on
the bike on the way to the
trews died okay on the street we don't
know so it's probably safer to keep
doing four
powers like I don't know every morning
or something
then here in the Tibetan if you're
interested uh there's uh it says Dr
choke choke you guys Dr choke
choke Dr choke choke means I'm so ready
to
go choke means ready and choke choke
means I'm so ready to
go
your your will is is
ready you talk to your
family they know what to do with your
organs they know what to do with your
body uh is it good to donate your
organs uh it's a little disturbing for
your by the when they are cutting them
out you are usually not completely dead
yet according to
Buddhism uh but it's a very great Karma
so I think it's worth it and I'm signed
up for
that so but it's a personal
decision but according to this teaching
you should make that
decision you know someone can use your
eyes someone can use your liver your
your
kidneys then uh try to make the decision
now
and let people
know and it's a cool idea to think that
somebody has eyes because you
prepared so I I personally I think it's
a cool
idea okay
uh he's goingon to do number
five which is prayer
okay
he says this is very beautiful he
says while you're done normal
people as they
die they are praying that they will go
to
heaven and
uh a
person as they
die they are thinking I hope I can take
other people's bad Karma with me when I
die okay I will just before I die I will
eat your bad seeds and then I
die and I pray that uh my death can help
some
people and I pray that after I die I can
help
people and he says look it's not wrong
if if
you if you haven't studied a
lot it's fine when you're dying to pray
I hope I can go to heaven that's okay if
you're not
experienced uh
practitioner that's
fine I was on a plane one
time and uh they they thought it was
going to crush you
know and all
my uh old church stuff came back to
me and I'm like Jesus take care of
me and I think that's
fine okay like you know I hope I meet
you and uh I think that's fine at the
same
time uh if you if you have this
teaching you can say Jesus I hope you
meet I me hope I meet you and I hope I
take some other people's bad seats with
me if it's me I cover
both I will take care of
both it means that practice dying
my Lama taught me every night to
practice after coffee meditation
practice your
dying as you fall
asleep practice those last few
minutes and uh I I pray I can come and
meet you Jesus or whatever is
comfortable for
you and then uh I hope I can take some
other people's negative seeds with
me I hope I can help other
people okay number
two okay he's out of order
[Music]
okay what is number two haveit
good
um he says it's very important during
your whole
life to keep having the
motivation that I would like to become a
Buddha on countless planets to help
countless
people so really The Habit part of the
dying part
okay
you do that while you're
alive and then it's automatic as you
die whatever was on your mind the most
while you were alive is going to come in
your mind when you
die so keep thinking about uh while
you're
alive keep having this motivation to
take care of people on countless
planets and I know it's not something
you think about
usually but it's a good
habit and it's not
Superstition it's it's stupid to think
that it's stupid to think we are the
only
planet it's very naive to think that you
know yeah of course there's other
planets you know of course there's other
cities like Beyond
guara so you know don't just pray for
people in
guara there's Phoenix there's Rimrock
Phoenix Rimrock pray for those
people and and don't think uh you know
guar is the whole
world and don't think Earth is the whole
universe it's the same
problem there's countless
planets and there's many other cities in
the
world so when you do your prayers you
know in English we say don't be
paroquial don't don't focus on
Rimrock
there's more cities than your home
City and there's more planets than your
home
planet and you know it doesn't hurt you
to pray for
them hope hope that you can serve them
someday
okay something strange happened
today Grandpa is exactly on
time I don't know
[Applause]
what in the in the did we cover five
dying ones I
think okay we covered five diamonds not
in order but we covered
them he has some final advice
here uh one of them is about and it's
and by the way there's very beautiful
teachings on how to
die and we we went through it in great
detail in about five years
ago if you're interested check the
what's that thing called the knowledge
base the knowledge spacee there's
10,000 free teachings there IDE is
the retreat in guar is too
expensive you know okay if you if it's
not worth eight hours work right which
is what it is it's about or I don't know
in the United States to come here is
like 12 hours of of
pay if it's not if it's not worth 12
hours of
pay then go online and see the knowledge
base
okaye there's
10,000 teachings by Grandpa
there and they are free okay so no
complaining and uh if if you want more
detail about how to
die uh I I suggest you listen to the
previous L teachings on
it if you're not sure what days those
were and I'm not sure we can ask
Tim okay and we talked about the the the
clear light and things like
that okay uh now he has a very
interesting instruction and Buddhism is
very
clear
and he says uh if you can try to you
ready just stay
there try to on your
right after the car HS
you
try to try to get on your right
side by the way it's it it's very it's
it's not stupid and probably you're
helping your
family if you if you say look uh I went
to retreat in in
guara they taught us how to die
properly and uh if I'm dying can you
please put me on my right side
and and it's beautiful it's a beautiful
thing okay and and maybe it's going to
help your family a
lot uh to talk about it you know and uh
for example they're not supposed to
touch your
head if it's possible to leave the body
for four or five
hours
and don't touch sorry don't touch the
feet uh and in a in America you have
it's leg illegal to keep a dead
body and I had this fight with the
police many
times I think it within 24 hours you're
required to put it in a cold storage or
something that's a law yeah
uh but you can help the
person and uh try not to touch them on
their
feet and when the police come and they
say we have to take the body you
know you can uh kind of hit it kind of
strong on the top of
hand uh it helps the mind to go to the
right
place
okay yeah all
right I I I had
a uh I was
um staying with a blind uh Mongolian
gese for five years or
[Music]
something uh he he liked to eat to tell
you the
truth and uh he will make Momos blind
you
know these are doom right you know what
do you call
those in English dumplings dumplings
yeah and he's
like and then one day he's
like he has a dumpling in his hand and
he's
like and I look at him you know he like
I like
gu he
like you
okay and he died like
that he died with the with the Momo
right here you
know and oh my God then uh I have to try
to get the Momo out of his
hand then I I asked my teacher what
should I do you know
he said you have to do the whole Vini s
with
him the good one is like three hours or
something and the police
came and they're like legally we have to
take him you
know I'm like where are you going to
take
him and he goes to the refrigerator in
the
hospital so I went with him to the
hospital in the in the ambulance
and I negotiate with the
hospital and they say if you stay in the
refrigerator you can you can stay with
[Laughter]
him
okay and I finished
the in the
refrigerator and uh you can do
[Laughter]
it so uh
you
know try the person on their right side
try to put the person on their
right and uh try to do some prayers for
them and some mantras
okay man is
fine if you know vaj manra if you met
the guara
teacher then you're very lucky
and they will teach you the higher
higher
mantras you just have to ask
them I asked them to teach more Diamond
way we had many meetings this
week with the teachers from
guara they are doing really really
good and they are learning a diamond way
very
well
so first of all I'd like to thank
them then I'd like to thank uh venerable
Jigme Venable Gil John Connie everyone
who's teaching me
if if I'm gonna die in Mexico I will
choose
guar uh because I can call one of them
to come and do
mantras if I live in guar I will let my
family know all those phone
number
and make some
preparations and then he can come and
sit in the
[Laughter]
refrigerator and by the way we should
you know if if if we are successful in
L we should have fun dying
also your heart is
clean did your
best you you collected good
seeds then okay I'm ready let's do
it every day is like dying
right tomorrow is like the next
life and we are so lucky to have this
teaching and we have somebody to help us
when we
die cool cool